Guide to the Program for Humanities in Medicine, School of Medicine, Yale University, Records of Howard M. Spiro as Director
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Program for Humanities in Medicine, School of Medicine, Yale University, records of Howard M. Spiro as director
1968-1999
RU 313
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
12.5
(10 boxes)
The records consist of administrative files, correspondence, and writings documenting the Program for the Humanities in Medicine at the Yale School of Medicine.
Yale University. Program for Humanities in Medicine
Spiro, Howard M. (Howard Marget), 1924-
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 27-E (YRG 27-E), Records of departments, offices, programs, and projects of the Yale School of Medicine.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the records is restricted. See Collection Contents for details.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession.
Biographical / Historical
The Program for Humanities in Medicine, Yale School of Medicine, was established by Dr. Howard M. Spiro in 1983 to foster an awareness of the links between the humanities and the arts and the practice of medicine.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of administrative files, correspondence, and writings documenting the Program for the Humanities in Medicine at the Yale School of Medicine.
Arts medicine; Medicine and the humanities; Universities and colleges -- Administration; Yale University -- Administration; Yale University. Program for Humanities in Medicine; Yale University. School of Medicine
- Records of Howard M. Spiro as director of the Program for Humanities in Medicine, Yale University, 1982-1999; Accession 2000-A-036
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted until Jan 1, 2034.
  - Editorial Board #1, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Editorial Board #2, 1990 (Box 1)
  - GI Fellow (Box 1)
  - Humanities in Med. General Information, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Spiro C.V. and Personal Information, Photos (Box 1)
  - Licensures (Box 1)
  - Humane Medicine (Box 1)
  - Worksheets and Expense Reports, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Court Cases (Box 1)
  - Spiro Writings Essays, Articles (Box 1)
  - Dr. Winternitz I, II, III, (drafts of book) (Box 1)
  - Griffin Hospital, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Medical Times Publication (Box 1)
  - Medical Theory Workshop, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Addresses Fellows, 1982-1984 (Box 1)
  - Outside Offers (Box 1)
  - Old Blues Gut Club Material (Box 1)
  - Spiro Articles xerox copies (Box 1)
  - Placebo book comments (Box 1)
  - Biphasic Animals (Box 1)
  - Plenum Publications (Box 1)
  - Legal Materials: malpractice cases (Box 2)
  - Raven Press I, II, III (Box 2)
  - Student/Doctor/ References and Recommendations I, II (Box 2)
  - Totts- Gap (Human Ecology) (Box 2)
  - Gas and Ends News (Box 2)
  - Yale Press, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Yale Journal of Bio. And Med., 1987 (Box 2)
  - "Winternitz" final Chapter 1 and notes (Box 2)
  - Literature and Med. Bibliographies, 1985-1989 (Box 3)
  - Donations:, 1993-1995 (Box 3)
  - Enid Peschel Literature topics Re: Med #1, #2, #3 (Box 3)
  - Schweitzer File (Box 3)
  - Humanities in Med. Affiliations' Vitaes (Box 3)
  - Coordinator Nance Cunningham's File (Box 3)
  - Amer. Institute's Life Threatening Illness and Loss (Box 3)
  - George Soros (Box 3)
  - Grant Trials (Box 3)
  - Advisory Boards (Box 3)
  - Death Symposium: Ars Moriendi (Box 3)
  - Schweitzer Program (Box 3)
  - Sponsored Events (Box 3)
  - Suggested Lecturers (Box 3)
  - McGovern File I (Box 3)
  - General Fundraising (Box 3)
  - Planning Text (Box 3)
  - Speakers for, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  - Fax, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - Humanities in Medicine Program General, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Lectures Summary, 1986-1994 (Box 4)
  - Speakers, 1991-1992 (Box 4)
  - Speakers, 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - Speakers, 1993-1995 (Box 4)
  - Speakers for, 1994-1995 (Box 5)
  - Speakers for, 1995-1996 (Box 5)
  - Speakers for, 1996-1997 (Box 5)
  - Seminars, 1995-1996 (Box 5)
  - Speakers and Program, 1997-1998 (Box 6)
  - Speakers and Program, 1998-1999 (Box 6)
  - Supplementary Material (Box 6)
  - Lois Goglia (artist) (Box 6)
  - Forms and Samples (Box 6)
  - Seminar meeting, 1983 March 1 (Box 7)
  - Contributors (Box 7)
  - NN (Kawzer) (Box 7)
  - List of people (Box 7)
  - Seminar, 1990 (Box 7)
  - NN (Box 7)
  - Speakers, 1987-1988 (Box 7)
  - Law Medicine Seminar (Box 7)
  - NN (Box 7)
  - NN (desk top to do) (Box 7)
  - NN (purpose of program, response to applications) (Box 7)
  - Seminar (Box 7)
  - Program (Box 7)
  - Potential Speakers (Box 7)
  - NN (Box 7)
  - NN (documents), 1984 (Box 7)
  - NN (journal) (Box 7)
  - Proposal 2 (Box 7)
  - Humanities in Medicine materials for brochure (Box 7)
  - Proposal (Box 7)
  - Bibliography for Humanities (Box 7)
  - Humanities program elsewhere (Box 7)
  - Law in Medicine vote (Box 7)
  - Law in Medicine correspondence (Box 7)
  - Law in Medicine mailing list (Box 7)
  - CV's advisory board (Box 7)
  - Book discussion group (Box 7)
  - Humanities Announcements (Box 7)
  - CT Humanities Council (Box 7)
  - CT Humanities Council Grant Applications (Box 7)
  - Picker Application (Box 7)
  - Supporting Material (Box 7)
  - National Fund Medical Education Grant old (Box 7)
  - National Fund Medical Education Grant new (Box 7)
  - Humanities Correspondence (Box 8)
  - Speakers Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Humanities Paper, 1985 (Box 8)
  - Speakers, 1988-1989 (Box 8)
  - Fall Symposium (Box 8)
  - Administration (Box 8)
  - Law in Medicine (Box 8)
  - Promotion (Box 8)
  - Humanities Correspondence (Box 8)
  - Editor of Medical Intern (Danbury) (Box 8)
  - Humanities Curriculum at other schools (Box 8)
  - Writings on Humanities in Medicine (Box 8)
  - Writings on Humanities in Medicine (Box 8)
  - Writings on Humanities in Medicine (Fall Seminar) (Box 8)
- Records of Howard Spiro as director of the Humanities in Medicine Program, circa 1968-1990; Accession 2002-A-053
  Restricted until Jan 1, 2025
  - Writings (Box 1)
  - Batman - piece on Pain (Box 1)
  - People to get advertisements about book (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - A (Box 1)
    - B (Box 1)
    - C (Box 1)
    - D (Box 1)
    - Esquerra (Box 1)
    - E (Box 1)
    - F (Box 1)
    - Family (medical) (Box 1)
    - Financial Report (Box 1)
    - G (Box 1)
    - H (Box 1)
    - I (Box 1)
    - J (Box 1)
    - Kaufmann (Box 1)
    - K (Box 1)
    - L (Box 1)
    - M (Box 1)
    - N (Box 1)
    - O (Box 1)
    - P (Box 1)
    - Q (Box 1)
    - R (Box 1)
    - S (Box 1)
    - T (Box 1)
    - U (Box 1)
    - V (Box 1)
    - W (Box 1)
    - X (Box 1)
    - Y (Box 1)
    - Z (Box 1)
  - Ortho-Ophtho - Osler (Box 1)
  - Misc. Writing (Box 1)
  - Writings (Box 1)
  - Typed Letters - Daily (Box 1)
  - Writings (Box 1)
  - Pieces (Box 1)
  - Pieces (Box 1)
  - Nat. History (Box 1)
  - Lecture Outline, etc (Box 1)
  - GI six lecture 2ndyear (Box 2)
  - Stress - Anxiety (Box 2)
  - Writings (Box 2)
  - Pharmacology - Drugs That Act on GI Tract, 1990 (Box 2)
  - GI lecture notes (Box 2)
  - Pharmacology questions (Box 2)
  - Pancreatitis, Acute and Chronic, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Residents Train in Hospital to Practice in Office (Box 2)
  - Abdomen - A Temple of Mystery (Box 2)
  - Training and Education information -notes/questions (Box 2)
  - A Preamble for the Formation of the Medical Associate, A Professional Service Division of Yale University School of Medicine, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Law - Medicine seminars, 1970's- 80's (Box 2)
  - Law - Medicine synopsis (Box 2)
  - Law - Medicine Sex with Patients (Box 2)
  - The Closing of the Rip Van Winkle Clinic (Box 2)
  - Notes Law - Medicine seminar, MD Code, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Patient Informed Consent (Box 2)
  - Felig Affair, Law - Medicine symposium (Box 2)
  - Law - Medicine, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Incompetent Patient (Box 2)
  - Malpractice (Box 2)
  - Minor Child (Box 2)
  - Nurses/MD conflict (Box 2)
  - Paternalism (Box 2)
  - Physician - Lawyer Relationships (Box 2)
  - Physician - Physician Relationships (Box 2)
  - Prisoner - 3rd party patients (Box 2)
  - Right to Know (Box 2)
  - Eppinger and Nazis that was not sent to Heidelberg (Box 2)